Hi!
I’m Jim Dowd at Zoar Outdoor.
In all of the presentations you’ve seen so far, I’ve been casting with a 7 ½ foot leader which connects the fly line through a thick section at the end of the leader at the fly line, and tapers all the way down through 7 ½ feet to a thin section that goes to the fly or in this case the yarn fly.
What this does is it provides a relatively invisible connection between you and the fish.
The taper allows the momentum to carry forward right down the fly line through the leader and into the fly.
A good general purpose selection to begin with would be a 7 ½ foot leader, because a relatively short leader is easier to use, it turns over the momentum much better.
So here for example this is a 7 ½ foot knotless 3X leader.
The strength on this leader is about 8 pound test.
This, on the other hand, is a 9 foot 3X leader, which is 8 pound test.
Different manufacturers have different configurations but basically Umpqua, Orvis, Frog Hair and others make wonderful leaders.
Make sure you start out with knotless.
When you buy the leader, it is a good idea to buy a spool of tippet which is the same diameter as the end of the leader.
And a little bit later I will show you a knot that you can use to connect new sections of leader as you replace the end when it gets chewed up by a trout, if you are changing flies and so on.